Supun Nakandala

Phone: (+1) 812-558-6888 3232 EBU3B CSE Email: snakanda@eng.ucsd.edu 9500 Gilman Drive Web: https://scnakandala.github.io La Jolla, CA 92093

Research Interests My research interest lies broadly in the intersection of Systems and Machine Learning. In this space, I operate as a data management researcher. My Ph.D. thesis work focuses on developing query optimization-inspired abstractions, algorithms, and systems to improve the efficiency, scalability, and usability of ML-based analytic workloads.

Education

University of California, San Diego

Sept 2017 - March 2022 (Expected)

Ph.D., Computer Science.

Thesis Title: Multi-Query Optimization for Deep Learning Systems

Committee Members: Arun Kumar (chair), Yannis Papakonstantinou, Geoffrey Voelker,

Lawrence Saul, Loki Natarajan

Courses: Principles of Database Systems, Database System Implementation, Advanced Data Analytics Systems, Data Models in Big Data Era, Advanced Compiler Design, Machine Learning, Recommender Systems and Web Mining, Algorithm Design and Analysis, Programming Languages

University of California, San Diego M.Sc., Computer Science. GPA: 3.97/4.00 Sept 2017 - June 2020

University of Moratuwa, Sri Lanka

Aug 2010 - April 2015

B.Sc., Computer Science. GPA: 4.11/4.20 Department Topper and Gold Medalist

Professional Experience

Microsoft - Research Intern

June 2021 - Sept 2021

Team: Microsoft Research Data Systems Group | Mentor: Vivek Narasayya Designed and evaluated resource management schemes for serverless databases.

Amazon Web Services - Software Engineering Intern June 2020 - Sept 2020

Team: Redshift | Mentor: Yannis Papakonstantinou

Designed and implemented components of Redshift ML, the in-database ML feature of the Redshift data warehouse that went to public preview.

Microsoft - Research Intern

June 2019 - Sept 2019

Team: Gray Systems Lab | Mentor: Matteo Interlandi

Designed and implemented the Hummingbird system, a compiler for translating classical machine learning pipelines into tensor computations for optimized ML scoring.

Indiana University - Research Software Developer Oct 2015 - Aug 2017

Team: Science Gateways Research Center | Manager: Marlon Pierce

Contributed to the development of the Apache Airavata system, which is a software framework to execute and manage computational applications and workflows.

Conference **Publications**

Nautilus: An Optimized System for Deep Learning-based Active Transfer Learning Supun Nakandala and Arun Kumar

SIGMOD 2022 (To Appear) | Paper

Cerebro: A Layered Data Platform for Scalable Deep Learning

Arun Kumar, Supun Nakandala, Yuhao Zhang, Side Li, Advitya Gemawat, and

Kabir Nagrecha

CIDR 2021 (Vision paper) | Paper

Cerebro: A Data System for Optimized Deep Learning Model Selection Supun Nakandala, Yuhao Zhang, and Arun Kumar VLDB 2020 | Paper

A Tensor Compiler for Unified Machine Learning Prediction Serving

Supun Nakandala, Karla Saur, Gyeong-In Yu, Konstantinos Karanasos, Carlo Curino,

Markus Weimer, and Matteo Interlandi

OSDI 2020 | Paper

Vista: Declarative Feature Transfer from Deep CNNs at Scale **Supun Nakandala** and Arun Kumar SIGMOD 2020 | Paper

Extending Relational Query Processing with ML Inference

Konstantinos Karanasos, Matteo Interlandi, Doris Xin, Fotis Psallidas, Rathijit Sen, Kwanghyun Park, Ivan Popivanov, **Supun Nakandala**, Subru Krishnan, Markus Weimer, Yuan Yu, Raghu Ramakrishnan, Carlo Curino CIDR 2020 | Paper

Incremental and Approximate Inference for Faster Occlusion-based Deep CNN Explanations

Supun Nakandala, Arun Kumar, and Yannis Papakonstantinou SIGMOD 2019 | Paper

Honorable Mention for Best Paper Award Invited to TODS 2020 Invited to SIGMOD Research Highlight 2020

Gendered Conversation in a Social Game-Streaming Platform Supun Nakandala, Giovani Cimpaglia, Norma Su, and Yong-Yeol Ahn AAAI ICWSM 2017 | Paper

Apache Airavata Sharing Service: A Tool for Enabling User Collaboration in Science Gateways

Supun Nakandala, Suresh Marru, Marlon Piece, Sudhakar Pamidighantam, Kenneth Yoshimoto, Terri Schwartz, Subhashini Sivagnanam, Amit Majumdar, Mark Miller PEARC 2017 | Paper

Apache Airavata Security Manager: Authentication and Authorization Implementations for a Multi-Tenant eScience Framework

 $\bf Supun \ Nakandala, \ Hasini \ Gunasinghe, Suresh Marru, and Marlon Pierce IEEE e-Science 2016 | Paper$

Anatomy of the SEAGrid Science Gateway Supun Nakandala, Sudhakar Pamidigantam, Suresh Marru, Marlon Pierce PEARC 2016 | Paper

Journal Publications

The CNN Hip Accelerometer Posture (CHAP) Method for Classifying Sitting Patterns from Hip Accelerometers: A Validation Study in Older Adults

Supun Nakandala*, Mikael Anne*, Marta M. Jankowska, Dori Rosenberg, Fatima Tuz-Zahra, John Bellettiere, Jordan Carlson, Paul R. Hibbing, Jingjing Zou, Andrea Z. LaCroix, Arun Kumar, and Loki Natarajan (* Co-first author) Medicine & Science in Sports & Exercise, 2021

Application of Convolutional Neural Network Algorithms for Advancing Sedentary and Activity Bout Classification Supun Nakandala, Marta Jankowska, Fatima Tuz-Zahra, John Bellettiere, Jordan Carlson, Andrea LaCroix, Sheri Hartman, Dori Rosenberg, Jingjing Zou, Arun Kumar, and Loki Natarajan

Journal for the Measurement of Physical Behavior, 2021 | Paper

Query Optimization for Faster Deep CNN Explanations
Supun Nakandala, Arun Kumar, and Yannis Papakonstantinou
SIGMOD Record 2020 (SIGMOD Research Highlight Award) | Paper

Incremental and Approximate Computations for Accelerating Deep CNN Inference Supun Nakandala, Kabir Nagrecha, Arun Kumar, and Yannis Papakonstantinou TODS 2020 (Invited Paper) | Paper

Vision, Workshop and Demo Publications

Vision, Workshop, Tensors: An Abstraction for General Data Processing

Dimitrios Koutsoukos, **Supun Nakandala**, Karla Saur, Konstantinos Karanasos, Gustavo Alonso, and Matteo Interlandi

VLDB 2021

Intermittent Human-in-the-loop Model Selection using Cerebro: A Demonstration Liangde Li, **Supun Nakandala**, and Arun Kumar VLDB 2021 | Paper

Compiling Classical ML Pipelines into Tensor Computations for One-size-fits-all Prediction Serving

Supun Nakandala, Gyeong-In Yu, Matteo Interlandi, and Markus Weimer NeurIPS 2019 MLSys Workshop | Paper

Cerebro: Efficient and Reproducible Model Selection on Deep Learning Systems Supun Nakandala, Yuhao Zhang, and Arun Kumar SIGMOD 2019 DEEM Workshop | Paper

Demonstration of Krypton: Optimized CNN Inference for Occlusion-based Deep CNN Explanations

Allen Ordookhanians, Xin Li, **Supun Nakandala**, and Arun Kumar VLDB 2019 Demo | MLSys 2019 Demo | Paper

 $\label{lem:materialization} \textit{Materialization Trade-offs for Feature Transfer from Deep CNNs for Multimodal Data} \ \textit{Analytics}$

Supun Nakandala, Arun Kumar MLSys 2018 Short paper | Paper

Research Impact

Microsoft open-sourced Hummingbird system and uses it in ONNX ML Tools 2020 Ideas from project Cerebro integrated into MADlib/Greenplum by VMWare 2020 CHAP models are now the state-of-the-art method for identifying sedentary behavior from hip-worn accelerometer data for public health applications 2020 Cerebro system is being used by behavioral science researchers at UCSD 2019 "Gendered Conversation in a Social Game-Streaming Platform" paper gains media attention and creates awareness about the bleak issue of sexism in online gaming 2017 APACHE AIRAVATA science gateways middleware and the SEAGRID science gateway are widely used by computational science researchers to execute and manage computational jobs on university clusters and national supercomputing infrastructure 2017

Patents

Pending US Patent Application: Query Optimization for Deep Convolutional Neural Network Inferences

Arun Kumar and Supun Nakandala

Pending US Patent Application: Accelerating Inference of Traditional ML Pipelines with Neural Network Frameworks

Matteo Interlandi, Markus Weimer, Saeed Amizadeh, Konstantinos Karanasos, Supun Nakandala, Karla J. Saur, Carlo Aldo Curino and Gyeongin Yu

Scholarships and Awards

SIGMOD research highlight award
Student grant to attend OSDI 2020
USENIX - 2020
SIGMOD best paper honorable mention award
NSF travel award to attend SIGMOD 2019
SIGMOD 2019
NSF - 2019
Gold medal for the best academic performance
Travel award to attend South Asia Workshop on Research
Mahapola higher education merit scholarship
SIGMOD - 2020
USENIX - 2020
SIGMOD - 2019
NSF - 2019
NSF - 2019
Oversity of Moratuwa - 2015
NUS Singapore - 2014
Govt. of Sri Lanka - 2010

Teaching Experience

Systems for Scalable Analytics-UCSD Winter 2020: TA for the inaugural offering of the course. Contributed to the design and implementation of the programming assignments of the course.

Advanced Data Analytics Systems-UCSD Spring 2019: Mentored graduate student research projects and conducted research paper discussions.

Service

Program Committee:

VLDB: 2022

DBAI@NeurIPS: 2021

External Reviewer:

VLDB: 2019

Mentoring Student Research Projects:

Liangde Li, MS UCSD 2021

Allen Ordookhanians, MS UCSD 2019

 ${
m Xin~Li,~MS~UCSD~2019}$

Advitya Gemawat, BS UCSD 2021 Kabir Nagrecha, BS UCSD 2021